<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Phoenix | Quick Notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://asquareb.github.io/blog/categories/phoenix/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://asquareb.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2021-12-19T12:43:40-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://asquareb.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[asquareb]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[JDBC Connection to Apache Phoenix]]></title>
    <link href="http://asquareb.github.io/blog/2016/03/31/jdbc-connection-to-apache-phoenix/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-31T12:27:36-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://asquareb.github.io/blog/2016/03/31/jdbc-connection-to-apache-phoenix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Phoenix provides a JDBC driver for Java client and hence can be connected to Phoenix by following the steps required to get a JDBC connection. As with JDBC drivers for other DBMS, there are are some Phoenix specific requirements to get a JDBC connection. For a non secure HBase cluster the Phoenix JDBC connection string should be of the form <code>jdbc:phoenix:&lt;ZK-QUORUM&gt;:&lt;ZK-PORT&gt;:&lt;ZK-HBASE-NODE&gt;</code>. The following is the code snippet to get a Phoenix JDBC connection object for a non secure HBase cluster.</p>

<!--more-->


<pre><code>Connection con = DriverManager.getConnection("jdbc:phoenix:nodea,nodeb,nodec:2181:/hbase");
</code></pre>

<p>To connect to a secure HBase cluster using a Kerberos user principal and keytab, the Phoenix JDBC connection string should be of the form <code>jdbc:phoenix:&lt;ZK-QUORUM&gt;:&lt;ZK-PORT&gt;:&lt;ZK-HBASE-NODE&gt;:principal_name@REALM:/path/to/keytab</code>. The following is the code snippet to get a Phoenix JDBC connection object for a secure HBase cluster.
<code>
con = DriverManager.getConnection("jdbc:phoenix:node1,node2,node3:2181:/hbase:peace@REALM.COM:/home/peace/peace.keytab);
</code>
If Kerberos principal and keytab is not used to connect to a secured HBase cluster, then the user running the code to make the connection should be defined in the Kerberos KDC and should have a valid TGT. The user running the code can verify whether they are in the correct KDC and have a valid TGT by running <code>klist</code> command . One key item to note is that to access a secure HBase cluster, the hbase-site.xml and core-site.xml of the target HBase cluster should be available in the classpath of the application.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
